Guide to the Lawrence Klein Papers, 1950s-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lawrence Klein papers 1950s-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Klein, Lawrence Robert
52.5 linear feet Extent: 40,000 Items
Nobel-prize winning economist and professor at the University of Pennsylvania's Wharton School. Collection includes Klein's correspondence, writings and drafts, economic research and subject files, organizational papers, and dissertations from Klein's many students. Contains significant amount of material from Project LINK, particularly from the late 1960s. Audiovisual recordings of the first LINK conference in 1969 will require reformatting prior to use. Also includes files from Klein's presidency of the National Academy of Science, his professorship at the University of Pennsylvania's Wharton School, and printouts from early economic computer programs and experiments.
RL.00786
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Research Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lawrence Klein Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1986 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Lawrence Robert Klein (b. 1920) is an American economist born in Omaha, Nebraska. Much of his work involves building macroeconometric models for economic forecasting. He earned his undergraduate degree at the University of California, Berkeley, in 1942, and studied under economist Paul Samuelson at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), completing his Ph.D. in 1944. Klein then worked on macroeconometric models at the University of Chicago. In the following years, he worked at the National Bureau of Economic Research, the Survey Research Center of the University of Michigan, and the Institute of Statistics at the University of Oxford, before accepting a position at the University of Pennsylvania in 1958. In 1968, he became the Benjamin Franklin Professor of Economics and Finance at the Wharton School. In 1980, he won the Nobel Prize in Economic Sciences.
In the 1960s, Klein sold econometric forecasts to benefit his department at the University of Pennsylvania. Wharton Econometric Forecasting Associates, Inc. grew from these efforts. In 1960, Klein visited and subsequently began working with economists in Japan. Klein also led research for the Social Science Research Council, and served as one of the principal investigators for Project LINK, which was created in 1968. Klein has traveled to Europe and Asia many times to give lectures, attend meetings, and work on collaborative projects. He and his wife, Sonia, have four children.
Sources:
Lawrence R. Klein, Britannica Online Encyclopedia, accessed November 30, 2011, http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/319969/Lawrence-R-Klein.
Lawrence R. Klein - Autobiography, Nobelprize.org, accessed November 30, 2011, http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economics/laureates/1980/klein-autobio.html.
Collection Overview
The collection includes Klein's correspondence, writings and drafts, economic research and subject files, organizational papers, and dissertations from Klein's many students. It contains significant amount of material from Project LINK, particularly from the late 1960s. Audiovisual recordings of the first LINK conference in 1969 will require reformatting prior to use. Also included are files from Klein's presidency of the National Academy of Science, his professorship at the University of Pennsylvania's Wharton School, and printouts from early economic computer programs and experiments.
The Dissertations series includes copies and drafts of dissertations and theses written by Klein's students and advisees during his tenure at the University of Pennsylvania. They are arranged in alphabetical order by the author's name.
The Subjects, Organizations, and Research series includes subject files and materials on various publications, research topics, projects, and organizations with which Klein worked. This series includes many materials from his career at the University of Pennsylvania, including teaching materials and committee information, as well as his presidency of the National Academy of Sciences. It has been arranged alphabetically by folder title.
The Project LINK series contains records related to that project, for which Klein served as principal investigator along with Bert Hickman, Rudolf Rhomberg, and Aaron Gordon. Included are materials from various meetings, research materials, and reports.
The Computer Printouts series contains computer printouts from an unknown project, possibly Project LINK, dating from the early 1980s.
The Correspondence series contains letters, memos, and faxes received or written by Klein. Much of the correspondence was exchanged with colleagues in the field of economics, and reflects collaborative research endeavors. Arranged loosely by correspondent within each year. Not every year has incoming correspondence.
Writings by Klein includes papers and speeches written by Lawrence Klein for journals, newspapers, editorials, and congressional testimony.
Writings by Others includes non-dissertation writings on economics collected by Klein for his own research or interest.
Audiovisual Materials contains audio recordings of the first worldwide Project LINK conference in 1969. This material will need to be reformatted prior to use.
There is also a small amount of Unsorted Miscellaneous material.
In addition, a small amount of electronic media has been removed from the collection and transferred to Duke's server. Please contact Research Services for access to this material.
Subject Headings
Klein, Lawrence Robert; University of Pennsylvania. Dept. of Economics; Wharton School; Project Link; National Academy of Sciences (U.S.); Nobel Prize winners; Economics; Economic history; Macroeconomics; Econometric models
Contents of Collection
- Dissertations, 1960s-2000, (14 boxes)
  Includes dissertations and drafts from Klein's students and other advisees, ranging in date from the late 1960s through 2000. Arranged alphabetically by author's name in record storage cartons, unless otherwise noted.
  - A-Be (Box 1)
  - Be-Broo (Box 2)
  - Brow-Fin (Box 3)
  - Fitz-Ham (Box 4)
  - Har-Hyun (Box 5)
  - Hyun-Mar (Box 6)
  - Mar-Mon (Box 7)
  - Mon-Par (Box 8)
  - Pir-Row (Box 9)
  - Row-Ste (Box 10)
  - Swa-Untitled (Box 11)
  - Untitled-Wei (Box 12)
  - Wei-Yeh, (1/2 size box) (Box 13)
  - Yoo-Z and loose pages, (1/2 size box) (Box 14)
- Subjects, Organizations, and Research, 1963-1991, (6 boxes)
  Contains subject files on various publications, economic research topics, and projects. Also contains organizational papers, including materials from Klein's presidency at the National Academy of Science, his work with the National Science Foundation, and his professorship at the University of Pennsylvania. Project LINK formed such a substantial portion of the materials that it is a separate series. Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject in record storage cartons.
  - Academy of Science, 1972 (Box 15)
  - AEA, 1966-1972, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - American Telephone and Telegraph, 1969 (Box 15)
  - Australia, 1971 (Box 15)
  - Brookings Institute, 1968-1971 (Box 15)
  - Business Week, 1969-1970, 1982, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Canada Council, 1968-1971 (Box 15)
  - Coal, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - DuPont - Brazil (Box 15)
  - Econometric Society, 1968-1970, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Federal Reserve Price Committee (Box 15)
  - Flow of Funds, 1970-1971 (Box 15)
  - Food and Finance Committee mailing lists (Box 15)
  - Ford Foundation, 1969-1970 (Box 15)
  - Harrison, Bennett (University of Maryland), 1968-1971 (Box 15)
  - IBM, 1967 (Box 15)
  - Independence Foundation, 1970-1971 (Box 15)
  - Institute of Social and Economic Research, 1968 (Box 15)
  - International Cooperation and Stabilization Policies Symposium, no date (Box 15)
  - International Economic Review, 1970-1973 (Box 15)
  - International Monetary Fund, 1968-1971 (Box 15)
  - Japan Economic Research Center, 1972 (Box 15)
  - MacMillan, 1968-1972 (Box 16)
  - Markham, 1970 (Box 16)
  - Maurice Falk Institute, Jerusalem, 1969-1972 (Box 16)
  - Mexico, 1970-1972 (Box 16)
  - National Academy of Science
    - Finance Committee Papers, 1976-1979, (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Nomination/election forms, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Chairman materials, 1985-1991, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Class membership, 1987-1989, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Membership nominations, 1989 (Box 16)
    - Ballots, 1989, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Membership selections, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
    - Nomination proposals, supporting materials, 1989-1990, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Ballots, 1990, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Membership committees, 1991 (Box 16)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1989-1992, (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - National Research Council, 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - National Science Foundation
    - Summer Research Institute application, 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Summer Research Institute application, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Proposal, 1972, (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 17)
    - NSF/CNRS Papers, 1976-1978 (Box 17)
    - NSF/CNRS Seminar, 1976-1978, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Negative Income Tax, 1968-1969 (Box 17)
  - Peace Research, 1969-1971 (Box 17)
  - Prentice Hall, 1971-1973 (Box 17)
  - Project "Hydra" Klausner, 1969 (Box 17)
  - Rubber, 1972-1973, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Russian Meetings, 1970 (Box 17)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1968-1970 (Box 17)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Survey Research Center, University of Michigan, 1968 (Box 18)
  - Technical report: Robust Non-Linear Data Smoothing, by Paul F. Velleman, 1975 (Box 18)
  - Tin, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Treasury Study, 1967-1969 (Box 18)
  - Wharton E.F.A., 1969-1970, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Vitae, 1973 (Box 18)
  - Vienna, 1970 (Institute for Advanced Studies) (Box 18)
  - University of Massachusetts, 1966-1971, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - University of Pennsylvania
    - Academic Calendar, 1978-1979 (Box 18)
    - Academic Planning Committee, 1972, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Benjamin Franklin University Professors, 1963-1972, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Bills, invoices, etc (Box 18)
    - Budget Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 18)
    - Budget Committee, 1972 (Box 19)
    - Committee on Economic History (Box 19)
    - Committee on Education Policy, 1972-1973 (Box 19)
    - Committee on Faculty Affairs, 1971 (Box 19)
    - Committee on University-State Relations, 1962-1966 (Box 19)
    - Committee to appoint a Dean for the Graduate School, 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Computer Center reports, 1968-1972, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - Computer numbers (Box 19)
    - Company Contributions to Forecasting Unit (Box 19)
    - Curriculum (Box 19)
    - Dean of Law School Committee, 1969 (Box 19)
    - Development Commission (Box 19)
    - Econometric Society meeting (Box 19)
    - Econometric Unit, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Economics Department, 1968-1970 (Box 19)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box 19)
    - Fels Institute of Local and State Government (Box 19)
    - Financial Statements, ER (Box 19)
    - Investment Banking Chair (Box 19)
    - Librarian search, 1969-1970 (Box 19)
    - Personnel Committee (Box 19)
    - Provost Search Committee, 1970 (Box 19)
    - Search for University of Pennsylvania Athletic Director, 1979 (Box 19)
    - Student recommendations, 1970-1973 (Box 19)
    - Sujan, 1970 (Box 19)
    - Summer employment (Box 19)
    - University Committee on Statistics Professors, 1963 (Box 19)
    - University Planning Committee, 1965-1972 (Box 19)
  - Virginia State College, 1970-1972, (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Wharton E.F.A., 1968-1971 and no date, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - Wharton Quarterly, 1971-1972 (Box 20)
- Project LINK, 1950-1996, (2 boxes)
  Contains materials on Project LINK, an international research project integrating various national econometric models into a global econometric model. (About Project LINK, UN DESA, accessed November 30, 2011, http://www.un.org/en/development/desa/policy/proj_link/index.shtml). Klein served as one of the principal investigators for this project. Tapes of the first worldwide Project LINK meeting can be found in the A/V for Project LINK, 1969 series.
  - Annual Meeting, Newport, RI, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Annual Meeting, Vienna, 1972 (Box 20)
  - Australia, 1970-1971 (Box 20)
  - Austria, 1969-1971 (Box 20)
  - Belgium Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 20)
  - Canada, 1968-1970 (Box 20)
  - European Meeting (Paris), 1968 (Box 20)
  - France (Box 20)
  - General correspondence and reports, 1968-1971, (9 folders) (Box 20)
  - General correspondence and reports, 1968-1973, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Germany (Box 21)
  - International Monetary Fund, 1968-1970, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Haley, 1968-1970 (Box 21)
  - Japan, 1968-1970, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - London meetings, 1970 (Box 21)
  - Meeting participants lists, 1987-1996, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Mini-LINK exercises, 1970s (Box 21)
  - Regional models, 1950-1970 (Box 21)
  - Research, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Sweden, 1968-1970, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - UNCTAD models, 1968-1970, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - U.K., 1968-1970 (Box 21)
  - World meeting prep, 1971-1973 (Box 21)
  - World meeting report, 1972 (Box 21)
  - World Outlook, 1983 (Box 21)
- Computer printouts, 1970s-1983, (3 boxes)
  - Printouts (Box 22)
  - Printouts (Box 23)
  - Printouts (Box 24)
- Correspondence, 1968-1997, (6 boxes)
  Includes letters, memos, faxes, etc. Years are generally arranged alphabetically by first letter of correspondents' surnames. Outgoing correspondence from 1987 is arranged chronologically in record storage cartons. Some additional correspondence can be found in the Subjects, Organizations, and Research and Project LINK series.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1971 O (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1971 P-1975 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 26)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1987 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1990 A-M (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1990 N-Z (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1991 A-Z (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1992 A-G (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1992 H-Z (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1993 A-Z (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1994 A-H (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1994 I-L (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1995 outgoing (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 January (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 2007 October (Box 30)
- Writings by Klein, (4 boxes)
  Includes articles, reports, papers, etc. written by Lawrence Klein. Arranged alphabetically by title in record storage cartons.
  - Writings by Klein, A-E (Box 30)
  - Writings by Klein, E-M (Box 31)
  - Writings by Klein, M-S (Box 32)
  - Writings by Klein, S-Z (Box 33)
  - Klein's loans, (4 folders) (Box 33)
- Writings by Others, (0.5 boxes)
  Includes articles, reports, papers, etc., written by people other than Klein. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Writings by Others A-Z (Box 34)
- Unsorted Miscellaneous, (0.5 boxes)
  - Miscellany (Box 34)
- Audiovisual materials, 1969, (1 box)
  Includes audio tapes of the first worldwide Project LINK conference in Hakone, Japan, in 1969.
  - Tapes (Box 35)